<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Cape Town Rocks</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="title_activity_rock_list">Rock List</string>
    <string name="title_activity_place_list">PlaceList</string>
    <string name="title_activity_maps">Map</string>
    <string name="tour_map_tooltip">Drag map to scroll</string>
    <string name="list_tooltip">Swipe up//down to scroll\n\nClick the names to go to the specific page</string>
    <string name="about_info">"This is the companion app for the 35th IGC's Building Stones of Cape Town tour, based on the book <i> The Building Stones </i> of Cape Town by Doug Cole. \n\nThe purpose of the walking tour is to examine the building stones in selected buildings, monuments
    and statues in central Cape Town. The building stones comprise sedimentary, igneous and
    metamorphic rocks and the mineralogy, texture and, in some sedimentary rocks, the sedimentary
    structure will be seen.\n\n Images provided by Rob Leyland. \n\n "</string>
    <!-- Key Colours -->
    <color name="CapeGSuiteCol">#EF8076</color>
    <color name="TableMountainCol">#00ABDC</color>
    <color name="MalmesburyCol">#945b3e</color>
    <!-- LOCATION VALUES -->
    <string name="loc_rocks_label">Stones found at this location:</string>

    <!-- loc_1 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_1">Bartolomeu Dias Statue</string>
    <string name="loc_1_coords">-33.917428, 18.428098 \n\n Roundabout at the intersection of the Heerengracht and Walter Sisulu Avenue.</string>
    <string name="loc_1_desc"> The statue was a gift from the Portuguese government to South
Africa on the occasion of the tercentenary celebrations of the landing of Jan van Riebeeck, but was
only unveiled in 1960 near the South African National Gallery and moved to the present site in about
1984. The statue is bronze and about 2.5 metres high, the sculptor being Professor Barata Feyo. It rests on a pedestal and a flat plinth of very light grey, coarse-grained, porphyritic granite of
the Cape Granite Suite. The pedestal was designed by the architect, Fernandes de Sá. The stone has a
sawn finish and contains lath-like orthoclase phenocrysts, up to 80 mm long. Grey to dark grey
xenoliths, a few of which have been partially assimilated by the granite, are also noticeable and
attain 100 mm in length. The porphyritic granite was possibly obtained from Mamre Quarry, near
Atlantis, since local quarries in the region of Kloof Nek, including the Higgo Quarry, had
already been closed for a considerable period by the time that this memorial was built.
\n\n
We cross the road on the southern side of the roundabout and briefly stop at a plaque
commemorating Bartolomeu Dias, which is mounted on a pedestal and base of the medium-grained
“Paarl Grey” granite, more extensive examples of which will be seen later on the tour. We proceed
southwest along the “island” between the two roads of the Heerengracht and pass numerous
blocks of sandstone with a sawn flat top for persons to sit. The sandstone is fine-grained, beige in
colour and cross-bedded in places. It is known commercially as “Golden Dawn” and is quarried from
Mookgopong (formerly Naboomspruit) in Limpopo Province. It is fluvial in origin and is from the Early
Jurassic Clarens Formation, Karoo Supergroup. At the southern end of the “island”, we cross the
exit road to Hertzog Boulevard and arrive at the War Memorial.</string>

    <!-- LOC_2 : -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_2">War Memorial</string>
    <string name="loc_2_coords">-33.918601, 18.426860 \n\n Traffic island in the middle of the Heerengracht</string>
    <string name="loc_2_desc">The War Memorial commemorates the 1st and 2nd World Wars and the Korean War. It consists of three bronze sculptures, which rest on
pedestals and plinths of beige-coloured, quartzitic sandstone of the Table Mountain Group, and four
bronze bas-reliefs (low relief panels) on the lower part of the pedestal. The sculptor was Vernon
March and the memorial was originally unveiled in 1924. The high central sculpture shows an
angel treading on a serpent that is wrapped around a globe, which represents the Earth. The lower
sculptures east and west of this central sculpture depict respectively, a South African soldier in East
Africa and a South African soldier in Flanders during World War I. The four bas-reliefs depict various
scenes from World War I. The memorial was originally erected at the bottom of Adderley Street close
to the original coastline and moved by eight metres when Adderley Street was widened in
1959, fourteen years after reclamation of the Foreshore. In 2013, it was moved again by
three hundred metres to its present position to make way for a new feeder station for the MyCiTi
bus rapid transit system.
        \n\n
The quartzitic sandstone is hammer-dressed and was probably exploited from loose boulders near
Kloof Nek (Bishop and Williams Quarry) and/or from quarries near Lakeside and Glencairn.It is fine- to coarse-grained, massive but cross-bedded in places, and contains scattered, white,
rounded, quartz pebbles and greenish-grey mudstone clasts. The pedestals and plinths surmount a
stepped podium constructed of light grey, medium-grained granite (Paarl Grey), which was taken
from quarries west of Paarl. The granite has a sawn finish and contains light grey to white, lathlike,
feldspar crystals, grey, glassy quartz crystals and black, flaky biotite crystals. Brown stains are
locally present, due to oxidation of fine-grained, cubic pyrite crystals.</string>

    <!-- loc_3 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_3">Van Riebeeck Statues</string>
    <string name="loc_3_coords">-33.919460, 18.425995</string>
    <string name="loc_3_desc">The statues are of Jan van Riebeeck and Maria de
la Quellerie. Both statues are bronze, about
three metres high and rest on pedestals and
plinths of quartzitic sandstone of the Table
Mountain Group supported on two-stepped
podiums of granite. The Jan van Riebeeck
statue was completed in 1899 and was
commissioned by Cecil John Rhodes as a
personal gift to the citizens of Cape Town, the
sculptor being John Tweed. It was placed at
the end of Adderley Street close to the original
shoreline near to the site where Van Riebeeck
was thought to have landed in 1652. The
Maria de la Quellerie statue was commissioned
by the Nederlandse van Riebeeck Comitee de
Heren Zeventien in 1952, the sculptor being Dirk
Wolbers, and was given by the people of the
Netherlands to South Africa in commemoration
of the tercentenary of Jan van Riebeeck’s arrival. It was originally placed near the Jan van
Riebeeck statue at the end of Adderley Street,
but both statues were moved to their present
site on the Foreshore in 1968.
        \n\n
    The quartzitic sandstone at the Jan van Riebeeck statue is buff to beige in colour, fine- to coarsegrained,
massive and, in places, stained orange or brown, as a result of the precipitation of ironbearing
minerals such as limonite. Scattered white, rounded, quartz pebbles, greenish-grey and dark
greenish-grey mudstone clasts and cross-bedding are present in some sandstone blocks. A pebble
bed can be seen in one block of the Jan van Riebeeck pedestal. These parameters are evidence of
deposition within an ancient river during the Ordovician Period, some 470 million years ago. The
quartzitic sandstone in the pedestals and plinths of the Maria de la Quellerie statue shows
similar properties. The two-stepped podiums at the foot of the plinths are constructed of different
local granites, i.e. light grey to very light grey, coarse-grained, porphyritic granite at the Jan van
    \n\n
Riebeeck statue and grey to light grey, medium-grained granite (Paarl Grey) at the Maria de la
Quellerie statue. This is almost certainly due to the different ages of the statues. For the Jan van
Riebeeck statue in 1899, coarse-grained, porphyritic granite was readily available from the Higgo
Quarry near Kloof Nek , but by 1952 when the Maria de la Quellerie statue was constructed,
all the granite quarries in the vicinity of Cape Town had been closed and the only accessible, local
Cape Granite was Paarl Grey from quarries west of Paarl. The quartzitic sandstone at the Jan van
Riebeeck statue could have been derived from loose boulders near Kloof Nek at a site named Bishop
and Williams Quarry and/or from quarries near Fish Hoek and Glencairn , while in
1952, this rock could still be obtained from Glencairn Quarry, which only closed in 1978.</string>

    <!-- loc_4 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_4">Number 1 Adderley Street</string>
    <string name="loc_4_coords">-33.920366, 18.426443</string>
    <string name="loc_4_desc">This forms a fifteen storey, concrete framed building, which was designed by the Department of
Transport in 1961. Natural stone is confined to the ground floor with the remainder of the
building comprising a facade of steel panels and gravel-clad, precast concrete attached panels.
Polished red granite (syenite) cladding is present on the window and door frames of the ground floor
in a sawn finish. It is accompanied by the 540 million year-old, light grey, medium-grained,
Paarl Grey granite, which forms the basework of the ground floor and the steps of the building in
a sawn finish. The red granite is medium- to coarse-grained, slightly porphyritic and contains
light grey to white, lath-like nepheline phenocrysts, up to 20 mm long, which are zoned and display a
light brown, light green or brownish-yellow core. Abundant pinkish-red, lath-like, feldspar crystals
and black, anhedral crystals of augite and hornblende are present. Sparse, white, glassy quartz can
be seen, but forms less than ten per cent of the rock, which is in fact classified as a syenite, rather
than granite. This syenite was quarried from an intrusive body in the Bushveld Complex at
Hammanskraal, north of Pretoria and is approximately 1400 million years old. The Paarl
Grey granite contains very light grey to white, feldspar crystals, grey to light grey, glassy quartz and
black, flaky crystals of biotite. Sparse dark grey to black xenoliths and rare brown stains due to
oxidation of pyrite are noticeable in this granite.</string>

    <!-- loc_5 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_5">The Castle</string>
    <string name="loc_5_coords">-33.926048, 18.428055 \n\n Darling St &#38; Buitenkant St, Cape Town, 8001, South Africa</string>
    <string name="loc_5_desc" formatted="false">Only the outer walls of the Castle near the entrance will be examined. The driveway leading
to the entrance is laid with grey to dark grey cobbles of medium- to coarse-grained leucogabbro,
which from mineralogical studies of a chipped sample, contains very light grey to grey plagioclase
feldspar (76&#37;), black augite (19&#37;), black orthopyroxene and an unknown accessory mineral (less than 1&#37;).
The cobbles were derived from loose boulders found within the castle grounds. The rock does not match any of the local basic rocks associated with the
Cape Granite Suite, since it lacks their typical alteration minerals, i.e. chlorite, epidote, sericite,
calcite and sphene. It probably originated somewhere
in northwestern Europe and was brought to Cape Town as shipping ballast by the Dutch in the 17th
and 18th centuries. The main part of the castle was built between 1666 and 1684 on a
pentagonal plan with bastions projecting from the walls. It was designed by Sebastion de Vauban and
Menno van Coehoorn and the gateway is the only Dutch Renaissance style remaining in South Africa. The Castle is almost completely constructed of dark grey, dressed and pointed building blocks of
hornfelsic slate and quartzitic slate of the Malmesbury Group. These were exploited from
Strand Street Quarry and other small quarries on Signal Hill, but the stone in the gateway was taken
from two quarries on Robben Island situated on the crests of broad anticlines where, in contrast to
Signal Hill, the bedding is more or less horizontal and slabs could be split using a cleavage
perpendicular to the strike of the anticlinal crest. The stone was originally bound using a lime or
clay mortar, but this was largely replaced with cement mortar, although several examples of the
original lime mortar can still be seen. The original entrance to the castle was built on the north side
facing the sea close to the original coastline, but this proved impractical as high tides lapped
the castle walls. A new entrance with a more elaborate gateway was therefore constructed in
1683 on the west side of the castle. As a result of weathering over a period of 300 years, the
gateway was restored in 1999 using precast moulded blocks that mimic the Malmesbury Group
hornfelsic slate with the original decorative stone blocks being stored within the castle in the Granary. Beige bricks in the tower above the gateway were
imported from Holland and the red bricks which form the parapet at the top of the stone walls, were apparently imported from England in the early 1800s.</string>

    <!-- loc_6 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_6">Anglo-Boer War Memorial</string>
    <string name="loc_6_coords">-33.925585, 18.424930 \n\n Darling St</string>
    <string name="loc_6_desc">This memorial consists of a marble statue of a soldier and female figure placed on an inscribed
marble pedestal of unknown origin. It was sculptured by Sir William Goscombe John in about 1904, and rests on a plinth and stepped podium constructed of very light grey, coarse-grained,
porphyritic granite of the Cape Granite Suite that was probably exploited from Higgo Quarry near
Kloof Nek. White to very light grey, orthoclase phenocrysts, i.e. elongate twinned laths up to
120 mm long, are conspicuous in this granite and small, flaky crystals of black biotite and silvery
muscovite, and dark grey speckled xenoliths, some schistose, also stand out.</string>

    <!-- loc_7 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_7">City Hall</string>
    <string name="loc_7_coords"> -33.925247, 18.423880\n\nOccupies the site bordered by Darling, Corporation, Longmarket and Parade
Streets</string>
    <string name="loc_7_desc">The City Hall is best viewed from Darling Street, where it faces the sun for most of the day. It was
completed in 1905 with the architects being Reid and Green, who won a competition for the design
of the building out of a total of seventeen entries. It took five years to complete and shows a
French Renaissance influence, as well as British colonial influences and resembles Leeds
Town Hall in England. The building has a two-storey facade, with projecting sections in the
centre and at either end, and has a prominent central tower. Corinthian porticos face both the
Grand Parade and Corporation Street.
    \n \n
    The City Hall has been the venue of two important events. On 21st April 1947, Princess Elizabeth (the
present Queen Elizabeth II) celebrated her 21st birthday with a grand ball in the City Hall and on 11th
February 1990, Nelson Mandela made his freedom speech, on the official day of his release from
prison, on the podium below the portico in front of the entrance in Darling Street.
        \n\n
        The striking beige colour of the building is a result of the superstructure being constructed of Jurassic
(~ 170 million years old) limestone named “Bath Stone” from Monks Park Quarries near Bath,
England. This contrasts with the light grey colour of the lower walling, basework pilasters and
plinths, which are built of coarse-grained, porphyritic granite of the Cape Granite Suite (~ 540
million years old), that was quarried from Higgo Quarry near Kloof Nek, Cape Town. “Bath
Stone” had originally been specified for the superstructure, but local masons objected to imported
stone so a beige-coloured, Permian-aged (~ 280 million years old) Karoo sandstone termed
“Steenpan” was decided upon. This sandstone was sourced from quarries situated near presentday
Sasolburg in the Free State Province, but due to hostilities associated with the Anglo-Boer War
coinciding with the start of construction in 1900, it was impossible to mine and transport stone by
rail from this area. It was then decided to use the original stone selected, “Bath Stone”, which
was transported by ship from Bristol, which is the closest port to Bath.
        \n\n
        The limestone has been extensively carved into ornamental facework and forms window frames,
arches, columns, cornices, pediments and balustrades around the exterior of the building.
When examined closely, numerous very fine-grained, white, beige, pink and light brown, rounded
spherules can be seen within a massive, very light grey to white calcareous matrix. The spherules are
referred to as ooliths and the limestone is an oolitic limestone. These ooliths were formed in
seawater with concentric layers of calcium carbonate being precipitated around a nucleus of quartz
or a small shell fragment. The roundness of the ooliths is due to their formation in an agitated, wavedominated
environment. In some blocks, the curved outline of sea shell fragments can be seen, as
well as minor, slightly sinuous, white calcite veins, which precipitated in fractures after the oolitic
sediment had lithified. These sinuous veins are called “snail-creep” by the quarrymen. A few blocks of limestone display cracking, flaking and spalling, as a
result of weathering, possibly associated with “acid rain”. The exterior of the building was
refurbished in 1996, with some blocks being replaced by precast concrete that was tinted to match
the limestone.
        \n\n
        The light grey, porphyritic granite displays its usual prominent features as seen earlier, namely very
light grey, white or beige, elongate laths (phenocrysts) of orthoclase, which are twinned and up to
100 mm long, sparse, dark grey, speckled xenoliths, up to 200 mm long, small, flaky crystals of black
biotite and sparse, silvery muscovite, and black, elongate crystals of tourmaline. Other less
conspicuous minerals are quartz (grey to light grey and glassy) and plagioclase (grey, light grey, white
and beige, lath-like crystals).
        \n\n
        Three other rocks are present in limited quantities. The polished columns of the Darling Street
portico are constructed of brownish-red, coarse-grained granite and those of the Corporation
Street portico of grey granite, both reported to have been imported from Aberdeen. The
pedestal moulds of the Darling Street columns are made of dark grey to black gabbro (known as
“Rustenburg Grey” in the Stone Trade). The brownish-red, coarse-grained granite is slightly
porphyritic with abundant feldspar phenocrysts. These are intensely microfractured with a red
ferruginous infill and there are prolific grey, glassy quartz crystals that show a bluish tinge. The
blueness in the quartz crystals is due to stress-induced fractures producing an internal reflection of
light, which is indicative of tectonic deformation, as is the intense microfracturing in the feldspar. Tectonically-deformed red granites are common in Sweden and Finland, where they are located
in the root zones of the Caledonian (450 to 350 million years ago) fold belt. It is probable that
the brownish-red granite originated in Sweden or Finland, since at the end of the 19th Century,
granite blocks were being shipped to the stoneyards of Aberdeen, where they were cut, turned and
polished before being sent to their final destination. The grey, polished granite in the columns of
the Corporation Street portico is slightly porphyritic and foliated, with phenocrysts of white to light
grey feldspar set in a groundmass of grey to light grey, glassy quartz, white, light grey and grey
feldspar and abundant black mafic minerals, principally biotite. Isolated dark grey to black xenoliths
are present. The fact that the granite is foliated rules out a Scottish origin and a Swedish or Finnish origin may again be applicable. The gabbro pedestal
moulds at the base of the Darling Street columns were inserted during refurbishment of the building
in 1996, and replaced badly spalled and eroded limestone blocks. Grey crystals of plagioclase and black pyroxene can be vaguely discerned in the
brightly polished blocks. The gabbro is derived from the Precambrian Bushveld Complex in the area
between Brits and Rustenburg, South Africa and is approximately 2 050 million years old.
    </string>

    <!-- loc_8 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_8">South African Mutual Life Assurance Society</string>
    <string name="loc_8_coords">-33.924284, 18.422315 \n\nCorner of Darling St and Parliament St </string>
    <string name="loc_8_desc">The most striking feature of the South African Mutual Life Assurance Society building is the extensive
sculpturing on polished granite cladding around the exterior of the building, making it one of
the most externally ornamented buildings in South Africa. A continuous bas-relief frieze
depicting South African history is present on the first floor level, with that on Darling Street showing
Van Riebeeck’s settlers meeting the Hottentots and the 1820 Settlers in the Eastern Cape. On
Parliament Street, seven subjects depicting the history of the four provinces are present. Several
other reliefs are present on individual granite slabs on the ground floor. The designer of the images
was Ivan Mitford-Barberton and they were carved by Messrs McKillop and Clift in about 1939. Polished granite cladding is present on the ground floor, with concrete slabs over the remainder
of the building. This 13-storey block was completed in 1939 and the architects were Louw and
Louw in association with F.M. Glennie. The rock consists of a pink, orange and red migmatitic to
gneissic granite, which contains grey to dark grey and black convoluted bands, patches, stringers and
streaks. It is named “Parys Granite” and was obtained from the vicinity of Parys, Free State,
possibly from the Municipal Quarry. It is approximately 3 100 million years old.
    \n\n
        Examination of the granite reveals the presence of pink to red feldspar containing a red ferruginous
infill within microfractures, very light grey to grey, glassy quartz and black biotite. Some slabs
contain cross-cutting, black and blackish-red, straight to sinuous quartz veins, up to 15 mm wide,
which are probably pseudotachylite veins. Such veins formed as a result of high-speed shock
waves caused by high-pressure impact of an extraterrestrial bolide, which caused an impact
structure, centred on the present village of Vredefort, 200 to 300 km in diameter approximately 2000
million years ago.
    </string>

    <!-- loc_9 UNEDITED -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_9">Damelin Building</string>
    <string name="loc_9_coords">-33.924018, 18.422051 \n\n 8 Darling St </string>
    <string name="loc_9_desc">This building lies adjacent to the South African Mutual Life Assurance Society building on the
opposite side of Parliament Street. It was previously named the “Permanent Buildings”. This
seven storey building with an inset columned portico on the fifth floor was designed by the architect
Stucke and completed in 1898. “Paarl Grey” granite is present throughout the building, in the
form of an ashlar facing with a sawn finish, and basework blocks in a rustic finish. The granite also
forms the window surrounds, cornices and inset columned portico. Decorative ornamentation in the
Fine Art Nouveau style has been sculptured on some blocks. The light grey, medium-grained
granite is slightly porphyritic with white, very light grey, light grey and beige feldspar laths, up to 15
mm long, set in a groundmass of grey to light grey, glassy quartz, white to grey feldspar and flaky
crystals of black biotite. Rare grey to dark grey, speckled xenoliths, up to 150 mm long, can be
observed in the granite and some slabs exhibit light brownish-yellow stains, probably as a result of
stone cleaning. Drill holes for originally extracting the granite blocks can be seen in Parliament
Street.</string>

    <!-- loc_10 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_10">First National Bank</string>
    <string name="loc_10_coords">-33.923443, 18.421289\n\n Corner Shortmarket and Adderley St </string>
    <string name="loc_10_desc">This six storey building was completed in 1933 and is the last major work of Sir Herbert Baker in
South Africa although A.T. Scott also contributed to the design. The building has raised,
inset, columned porticos with four simplified Corinthian columns between the third and fifth floors
on both Adderley and Shortmarket Streets. Cape Dutch Revival teak windows and half shutters are
present on the façade. A bronze descriptive plaque near the Adderley Street entrance outlines
the history of the site followed by a paragraph stating: “The bank moved into the new building on 22
July 1933. The white Table Mountain Sandstone of its walls was taken from a specially opened quarry
near Ceres: The travertine and marble used for the walls and floor of the banking hall were specially
imported from Italy”. This assumed Table Mountain Sandstone forms ashlar over the entire facade
and builds the portico, columns, window surrounds and cornices. It was obtained from a quarry near
Mitchell’s Pass and reputedly, more stonemasons were engaged on this project than on any other
since the construction of the Union Buildings in Pretoria in 1910. The sandstone is light beige in
colour, fine- to medium-grained, massive and quartzitic. Vestiges of cross-bedding and horizontal
bedding are present in a few slabs and isolated vugs containing medium-grained crystals of quartz
occur in places. Silvery, flaky crystals of sericite are present. The sandstone lacks some of the
characteristic features of the Table Mountain Group sandstones, i.e. a coarse-grained texture,
isolated rounded pebbles of white quartz and orange- to brown-coloured iron stains, as previously
seen in the Van Riebeeck statues at location 3. It resembles the quartzitic sandstone found within the
phyllites and shales of the late Precambrian Malmesbury Group at the southern end of Mitchell’s
Pass. The ubiquitous Paarl Grey medium-grained granite in a rustic and sawn finish forms the
plinth of the building, as well as steps and abutments around the entrance.</string>

    <!-- loc_11 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_11">Pearne Building</string>
    <string name="loc_11_coords"> -33.924144, 18.421236 \n\n 23 Adderley Street</string>
    <string name="loc_11_desc">This building was built in 1903 and was designed by architects MacGillivray and Grant. It has four
storeys with a narrow Dutch gable and is one of the few remaining examples of a type of building
based on a Dutch town-house still surviving in Cape Town. The name of the original owners, C.H.
Pearne and Company and their advertisement “Ladies Outfits, Mantles and Costumes”, is still in
place in the upper part of the facade. An inaccessible beige sandstone is present as ashlar on the first
floor and on the verandah, as well as on the first to third floors of the building. This sandstone is
probably a Karoo sandstone and was most likely extracted from quarries in the vicinity of Sasolburg
or Vereeniging, which had access to the railway from Cape Town during the time of construction, i.e.
after 1892. These sandstones tend to be friable, in contrast to those of the Table Mountain
Group, and are Permian in age (~ 280 million years old).
    \n\n
    Four columns are present on the ground floor in front of the building and consist of red granite. This
granite is coarse-grained, porphyritic with red feldspar phenocrysts up to 30 mm long, which display
microfracturing. These are set in a groundmass of white to light grey feldspar with incipient
ferruginisation (red colouring), grey to light grey glassy quartz and black mafic minerals (mostly
biotite and possibly hornblende). The deep red colour of the feldspar and their microfracturing is
characteristic of Swedish or Finnish granites, which are located in the root zones of the Caledonian
fold belt where deformation continued after their original intrusion. It is most likely that, as in
the case of the red granite columns at the City Hall, the quarried blocks were first shipped to the
stoneyards of Aberdeen for cutting, turning and polishing before being transported to Cape Town.
The columns have a base block composed of a greyish-black, coarse-grained igneous rock identified
as larvikite. Unfortunately, these have been painted black since compilation of the Building Stones
Guidebook by Cole and the iridescent shimmering effect on the polished surface typical of
larvikite can no longer be observed.
    \n\n
    The neighbouring two buildings on the southwestern side have a colonnade with four columns
supporting a first-floor verandah. The columns comprise polished, grey, coarse-grained, porphyritic
granite containing very light grey, lath-like, feldspar phenocrysts, up to 20 mm long, which are
commonly stained light brown. Black, speckled xenoliths are noticeable, but less obvious grey to light
grey, glassy quartz, grey to very light grey feldspar and black mafic minerals are present in the
groundmass. The source of this granite is unknown. The base blocks of the granite columns have
been painted black, but a previously damaged one showed it to be composed of beige, very fine- to
fine-grained sandstone.</string>

    <!-- loc_12 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_12">Constitution House</string>
    <string name="loc_12_coords">-33.924232, 18.420570 \n\n 124 Adderley St </string>
    <string name="loc_12_desc">This was formerly named Regis House and was constructed around 1955. It is a fourteen storey,
concrete framed building that is mainly clad with precast concrete panels with an exposed
aggregate finish. However, polished cladding and floor tiles of white, cryptocrystalline marble are
present on the ground floor. This marble contains grey, dark grey and light brownish-grey blotches
and convoluted stringers and layers, which are characteristic of the 700 to 600 million year old
Vanrhynsdorp or Namaqua Marble. This marble occurs in a northwest-trending belt in the
vicinity of Vanrhynsdorp and has been quarried intermittently since the 1920s.</string>

    <!-- loc_13 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_13">Reserve Taj</string>
    <string name="loc_13_coords">-33.924461, 18.420319 \n\n 130 Adderley St</string>
    <string name="loc_13_desc">The Reserve Taj, formerly the ABC Branch of Standard Bank, is a five storey, concrete framed
building that was completed in 1931, the architects being Black and Fagg. A striking, light brown,
precast concrete ashlar that resembles sandstone, is present from the second floor upwards. Fluted
Ionic columns composed of the same material occur on the second and third floors with a prominent
overhanging cornice at the top of the third floor. The familiar light grey, medium-grained granite
(Paarl Grey) forms a rustic basework on the ground floor and cladding on the ground and first floors.</string>

    <!-- loc_14 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_14">ABSA Building</string>
    <string name="loc_14_coords">-33.924581, 18.420235\n\n134 Adderley St</string>
    <string name="loc_14_desc">The ABSA Building is a prominent thirteen storey,
concrete framed block that faces down Bureau
Street on the opposite side of Adderley Street. The date of construction is unknown, but
sandstone panels, which clad the building, were attached in 1957, as indicated on a
metal descriptive plaque fixed to the ground
floor, which also states that the architects were
Kok and Orsmond. Two quartzitic sandstones are
present, but a few panels consist of fine-grained
granite. A beige or very light grey to creamy
white, fine- to medium-grained quartzitic
sandstone that is commonly stained brown due
to precipitation of iron-bearing minerals
occurs on the lower part of the facade, where it
extends up to the third floor in the central part
of the building, and is also present on four inset
vertical facings, which extend to the top of the
building. It is cross-bedded in places and
contains scattered white, rounded, quartz
pebbles and minor greenish-grey,
elongate mudstone clasts. It was derived from
the Table Mountain Group, possibly from
Glencairn Quarry near Fish Hoek, which was still
working in 1957, and the sandstones were
dressed and polished in Pretoria.
    \n\n
    The other quartzitic sandstone clads the remainder of the building, including some inset vertical
facings on the ground, first and second floors. It is light grey, fine-grained and is characterised
by flaky crystals of silvery muscovite, which are present on the surface of the panels, coinciding with
the bedding planes. It mimics the Lekkersing quartzite that is quarried from east of Port Nolloth,
South Africa and is approximately 700 to 600 million years old, more or less correlating with the local
Malmesbury Group. The fine-grained granite occurs on the lower part of the facade in isolated slabs.
It is light brownish-grey or beige in colour, generally homogenous and contains sparse feldspar
phenocrysts set in a matrix of glassy quartz, beige and/or very light grey feldspar and black biotite. Its
origin is unknown.</string>

    <!-- loc_15 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_15">Temple Chambers</string>
    <string name="loc_15_coords">-33.924713, 18.420076 \n\n Corner of Wale St and Adderley St</string>
    <string name="loc_15_desc">This building lies on the corner of Adderley and Wale Streets and was originally built as a
three storey structure in 1894 by G.M. Alexander and extended to six storeys in 1930. A Van der
Stel Foundation tablet reads “Site of the Hospital of the Netherlands East India Company 1697 or
1699 - 1782". The present building has mostly been plastered, but the basework is composed of
porphyritic granite of the Cape Granite Suite that was probably taken from the Higgo Quarry near
Kloof Nek. Participants should note the prominent very light grey to white orthoclase
phenocrysts (elongate laths up to 120 mm long), some of which show twinning. Metal columns,
which support a canopy above the pavement, are supported on bases made of the well-known, light
grey, medium-grained granite (Paarl Grey) of the Cape Granite Suite seen in several of the previouslyvisited
buildings. The same granite is present diagonally across the street, where it forms the plinth
of the Smuts Statue (location 16).</string>

    <!-- loc_16 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_16">Smuts Statue</string>
    <string name="loc_16_coords">
-33.925067, 18.420124 \n\n Corner of Adderley St and Government Ave</string>
    <string name="loc_16_desc">The bronze statue of J.C. Smuts is twice life size and comprises a massive seated figure. It was
erected in 1973 and is the last major work of the sculptor Ivan Mitford-Barberton. The granite was
probably taken from Clift’s Quarry, west of Paarl and is light grey, medium-grained, slightly
porphyritic and contains very light grey to white, microperthite phenocrysts up to 20 mm long.</string>

    <!-- loc_17 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_17">St. George\'s Cathedral</string>
    <string name="loc_17_coords"> -33.924776, 18.419294 \n\n 5 Wale St</string>
    <string name="loc_17_desc">The first cathedral, which began as the Church of St George in 1830, was designed by John Skirrow
and was based on the temple-fronted and towered church of St Pancras in London that had been
completed in 1822. With the arrival of Bishop Robert Gray in 1848, St George’s became a
cathedral. The new cathedral was built alongside the first building from 1901 onwards, using the
architects Herbert Baker and Francis Masey. It is built of quartzitic sandstone of the Table Mountain
Group in a rustic finish and has an Edwardian Gothic Revival style with a “Broseley” tiled roof.
Construction occurred intermittently with the north transept being added from 1930 until 1936
under the direction of architect F.K. Kendall, who amended Baker’s original design. In 1957, the south
transept was completed under C.D. St Leger and the bell tower was the last fixture to be added in the
1980s. The first cathedral was finally demolished in 1954.
    \n\n
    The sandstone is buff to beige in colour, fine- to coarse-grained, massive and, in places, cross-bedded
and stained brown due to precipitation of iron-bearing minerals. Quartz grains in the sandstone are
rounded to subangular and fine-grained mafic minerals are rare. Isolated white, rounded, quartz
pebbles are present. The sandstone was almost certainly derived from loose boulders near
Kloof Nek, including a site named Bishop and Williams Quarry, and also from quarries in the
vicinity of Muizenberg and Fish Hoek.
    \n\n
    Two varieties of slate form the steps and paving slabs in front of the cathedral and along its western
side. One, which is dark grey or dark greenish-grey in colour, is hard and cleaved in places,
and ripple marks are present on a few slabs, as well as siltstone and sandstone beds, up to 7 cm
thick. The latter are prominent along the western side of the cathedral, where load casts, ball-andpillow
structure and lenticular bedding can be seen. Horizontal bedding is also present and these
siltstone and sandstone beds were probably deposited by turbidity currents. This slate was
apparently obtained from quarries in the Malmesbury Group rocks on Robben Island during
construction of the first cathedral in the 1830s. In contrast, the other slate, which is very dark
grey and is randomly mixed with the Malmesbury Group slate, is particularly abundant on
the upper podium and steps in front of the cathedral and lacks any sedimentary features. However, it
does show a well-developed cleavage and silvery muscovite flakes on some slabs. It resembles slate
found in the Swartruggens area, North West Province, which formed as a result of burial
metamorphism and thermal metamorphism during intrusion of the igneous rocks of the Bushveld
Complex between about 2060 and 2050 million years ago.</string>

    <!-- loc_18 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_18">Mandela-Rhodes Building</string>
    <string name="loc_18_coords"> -33.924283, 18.419383 \n\n 150 St. George\'s Mall</string>
    <string name="loc_18_desc">The Mandela-Rhodes Building, originally named the Rhodes Building, was designed by Herbert
Baker and Francis Masey and was completed in 1902, some 6 months after Cecil Rhodes’s death.
It is a Cape Revival style building, steel or concrete framed, with five storeys and an attic. Dutch-
Flemish gables are present at attic level and the top floor has an engaged squat colonnade
supporting a granite cornice. Porphyritic Cape Granite from the Higgo Quarry predominates in
the building, forming a complete ashlar facade, together with balconies, window surrounds, a squat
colonnade, cornice, parapet, gables and entrance steps. Some decorative ornamentation has been
carved on the granite. The granite can be inspected at street level, where the basework has a rock
finish. The granite is light grey, coarse-grained and porphyritic with very light grey, orthoclase
phenocrysts, up to 80 mm long with twinning. The groundmass consists of grey to light grey, glassy
quartz, white, light grey and grey feldspar, black biotite and rare silvery muscovite. Sparse, black,
elongate tourmaline crystals, which, in places, cluster into clots, and dark grey, speckled xenoliths
are present.</string>

    <!-- loc_19 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_19">Mandela-Rhodes Place</string>
    <string name="loc_19_coords">-33.924052, 18.419103 \n\n Wale St </string>
    <string name="loc_19_desc">This was originally Syfrets Bank, later becoming Nedcor Investment Bank and finally Mandela-Rhodes
Place. The building is a steel or concrete framed building with six storeys and two attic levels. It has a
symmetrical facade and was designed by Franklin Kendall in the Arts and Crafts tradition, being
completed in 1927. There are Ionic columns in front of a recessed balcony on the third and
fourth floors, together with a balustrade and main cornice. The top levels rise to twin square copper
roofed corner turrets and attic dormers. Paarl Grey granite forms rusticated building blocks on the
ground floor, as well as the steps and cladding around the entrance. The upper level window
surrounds, Ionic columns, balustrade and cornice are built of inaccessible, beige-coloured sandstone,
and red facebrick walling is present between the first floor and the attic level corner turrets. The
sandstone is probably a Permian Karoo sandstone and may have been sourced from the former
Transvaal, South Africa, which given the date of the building, was most likely transported by rail
from quarries near Vereeniging or Wolwehoek, near present-day Sasolburg. The Paarl Grey
granite is typically medium-grained and slightly porphyritic. The contrast between the two local Cape
Granites can be seen where this building is juxtaposed against the Mandela-Rhodes Building.</string>

    <!-- loc_20 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_20">Bishop Gray Monument</string>
    <string name="loc_20_coords"> -33.924296, 18.419567 \n\n 119 St. George\'s Mall</string>
    <string name="loc_20_desc">The monument was originally erected in Wale Street in 1876 in front of the old cathedral before
being re-positioned in the Cathedral grounds near Queen Victoria Street and finally moved to its
present site in 1992 when St. George’s Street was converted into a mall. Robert Gray was the first
bishop of Cape Town. After his death in 1872, William Butterfield, who was an architect and lifelong
friend of Robert Gray, designed a memorial to him in the form of a cross on a column of granite set
on a pedestal and plinth of various rock types. The monument, which is about seven metres
high, essentially comprises an Ionic column, surmounted by a ball and metal cross, all set on a
pedestal with corner urns and pillars, resting on a plinth and stepped podium.
    \n\n
    Most of the stones were imported from
Great Britain, and the author is grateful
for the assistance of Professor Eric
Robinson from University College,
London, who identified most of these
stones with reasonable accuracy. The
Ionic column, corner pillars on the
upper part of the pedestal and two
central cladded slabs on the lower part
of the pedestal are composed
of polished, reddish- pink, medium- to
coarse-grained granite obtained from
north of Aberdeen, Scotland and known
in the Stone Trade as “Peterhead
Granite”. This granite can be
recognised by its colour, texture and
square shapes of the pink and white
feldspar phenocrysts.
Other minerals present are light grey to
dark grey, glassy quartz and black or
greenish black mafic minerals, including
flaky biotite. A few dark grey speckled
xenoliths occur and the granite is
Devonian in age (~ 400 million years
old). The basal part of the pedestal,
cornices, urns and surrounds of the
“Peterhead Granite” slabs are
composed of beige and creamy white
limestone.
    \n\n
    The limestone consists of rounded spherules called ooliths, and shell fragments set in a very finegrained,
calcareous matrix. Some limestone slabs are considerably shell-rich, whereas others contain
sparse shell fragments and are highly oolitic. Moldic cavities are present, where the shell fragment
has been weathered out. The limestone is “Portland Stone” from the small Isle of Portland in Dorset,
England. It was formed as a result of calcium carbonate precipitation in seawater during Jurassic
times about 150 million years ago. The lime-rich sediments were transformed into limestone due to
burial beneath younger sediments and diagenesis over millions of years. We have already seen
rounded ooliths in the “Bath Stone” limestone at the City Hall and they were formed by calcium
carbonate being precipitated in concentric layers around a nucleus of quartz or a small shell fragment
in an agitated, wave-dominated environment. The limestone is pitted and spalled due to weathering,
possibly associated with “acid rain” and some slabs have been cement mortar repaired. A polished,
very light grey to white, fossiliferous limestone makes up the central cladded slabs, one with a carved
decorative inscription, on the upper part of the pedestal, and another on the opposite
southern side, with an attached white marble cross and two hemispheres. The limestone, which is
considerably harder than the Portland Stone, is massive, cryptocrystalline and contains abundant
straight, hollow, open and tapering tube-like structures, up to 0.2 m long and 40 mm wide.
Transverse sections are normally circular or oval and transverse partitions in the walls of the

structure are approximately 10 mm apart. These tube-like structures are probably the fossilised
stems of crinoids, commonly referred to as “sea-lilies”. The limestone is Early Carboniferous in
age (~ 350 million years old) and would have had a similar origin to that of the younger Portland
Stone. It was possibly exploited from quarries in Derbyshire, England. The white marble cross and hemispheres are inaccessible, but can be seen to be
massive and cryptocrystalline with sparse, light grey, convoluted stringers and layers. This marble is
thought to be Carrara Marble from Italy.
    \n\n
        The corner pillars on the lower part of pedestal are constructed of reddish-brown, very fineto
fine-grained, massive and slightly friable sandstone containing iron-stained, subrounded to
rounded, “millet-seed” quartz grains. This sandstone matches the New Red Sandstone of the British
Isles and represents an ancient desert sand dune of Permian age (~ 270 million years old). The
distinctive colour indicates that it was probably quarried from Mansfield in Nottinghamshire, England.
        \n\n
        The remaining building stones are from South Africa, but one of these was substituted for the
original British stones when the monument was moved to its present site in 1992. This stone, which is a beige, very fine- to fine-grained sandstone from
Ficksburg, replaces two central cladded slabs of “Peterhead Granite” that had been damaged on the
lower part of the pedestal, and the badly weathered “Portland Stone” border of another granite slab
on the southern side of the pedestal. The sandstone is massive and composed of very light grey,
subangular to subrounded, glassy quartz and feldspar grains, black, flaky biotite grains and sparse
greenish-grey, elongate mudstone clasts. It was probably quarried from the upper part of the Triassic
(~ 220 million years old) Molteno Formation, with the original sediments being deposited in
rivers, after which they eventually became consolidated into sandstone.
        \n\n
        The plinth and steps of the podium are composed of very light grey, coarse-grained,
porphyritic granite of the Cape Granite Suite, which was possibly exploited from the Higgo Quarry in
the vicinity of Kloof Nek. The twinned orthoclase phenocrysts (lath-like crystals up to 60 mm
long) characteristic of this local granite, are again conspicuous. The paving slabs of the stepped
podium consist of dark grey to black, finely cleaved slate, which was probably added during
the 1992 move. Note the presence of silvery muscovite flakes in some of the slabs. The slate is similar
to that seen outside St George’s Cathedral and is from Pretoria Group rocks in the area
between Mazista and Swartruggens in the North West Province.
    </string>

    <!-- loc_21 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_21">Taj Hotel</string>
    <string name="loc_21_coords">-33.924351, 18.419939 \n\n 1 Wale St </string>
    <string name="loc_21_desc">This building was originally the Reserve Bank, which later became the Board of Executors Building
and finally, in 2010, was converted into the Taj Hotel. The architectural style is Cape Italianate and it
was drawn up by the architect James Morris, who won an award for its design. The building
has a basement and five storeys and was finished in 1929. It contains bronze gates, grilles and teak
sash windows and metal shutters. The building abounds with the locally-produced Paarl Grey granite,
which takes the form of an ashlar facade, the entrance steps and cornice, and rustic building blocks
on the ground floor. Carved granite ornaments are also present. The granite is similar to that
previously seen, being slightly porphyritic with lath-like phenocrysts of white and very light grey
feldspar, up to 20 mm in length, set in a groundmass of white to grey, rectangular-shaped feldspar,
grey to light grey, glassy quartz and black flaky biotite. Rare dark grey speckled xenoliths, up to 80
mm long, are present.</string>

    <!-- loc_22 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_22">The Reserve</string>
    <string name="loc_22_coords">-33.924144, 18.419931 \n\n 111 St George's Mall</string>
    <string name="loc_22_desc">The Reserve was formerly the ABC Branch of Standard Bank and extends through to the Reserve Taj
in Adderley Street, which we have already seen at location 13. Both buildings have an identical
façade and building stones. The Reserve building is concrete framed with five storeys and was
completed around 1931 using the architects Black and Fagg. The ubiquitous Paarl Grey granite is
present as rustic basework on the ground floor and cladding on the ground and first floors. Some
decorative heads and artwork have been sculptured on the ground and first floors. The granite
cladding extends along the ground floor and entrance of the adjacent building to the southwest,
Number 117 St. George’s Mall. Light brown, precast concrete ashlar that resembles sandstone, is
present from the second floor upwards, and builds fluted Ionic columns on the second and third
floors, and a prominent overhanging cornice at the top of the third floor.</string>

    <!-- loc_23 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_23">Equity House</string>
    <string name="loc_23_coords">-33.924105, 18.420030 \n\n Corner Church St and St George's Mall</string>
    <string name="loc_23_desc">Equity House was previously named Traduna House, and shows Art Nouveau overtones in finely
worked granite. It was designed by the architects, MacGillivray and Grant, and is a six storey,
steel or concrete framed structure that was built between 1906 and 1907. The locally-produced
Paarl Grey granite dominates the building in the form of a complete ashlar façade, which
resembles that already seen at location 21, the Taj Hotel. Artwork and decorative ornamentation have
been sculptured onto this granite on the fifth and sixth floors. Additionally, black lardalite, a
coarse-grained, nepheline syenite characterised by rhomb-shaped feldspar crystals, and large crystals
of grey nepheline, form polished street-level cladding.
This igneous rock is located near Larvik, Norway, is Early Permian (~ 292 million years) in age and
resembles larvikite, but does not display the blue iridescent shimmering effect on the polished
surface.</string>

    <!-- loc_24 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_24">118 and 116 St. George\'s Mall</string>
    <string name="loc_24_coords">-33.923250, 18.420467 \n\n </string>
    <string name="loc_24_desc">The United Building at 118 St. George’s Mall is a ten storey, concrete or steel framed structure that
was probably completed in 1938. It has a similar layout to that of Equity House and the Taj
Hotel, i.e. a complete Paarl Grey granite ashlar facade. However, decorative artwork and
ornamentation are lacking and a few granite slabs show light brown iron stains, possibly due to
cleaning chemicals used in 1975. On the adjacent building, 116 St. George’s Mall, Paarl Grey
granite is limited to cladding on the ground floor in a rustic finish. The remainder of the six storey
concrete or steel framed building is plastered and it was constructed in approximately 1926.</string>

    <!-- loc_25 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_25">Protea Assurance Building</string>
    <string name="loc_25_coords">-33.923250, 18.420467 \n\n Longmarket Street, Corner St Georges Mall, </string>
    <string name="loc_25_desc">This nine storey, concrete framed building was completed in 1930 using the design of the architects,
Jones and Adams, and was renovated in 1965, which included an arcade linking through to
Greenmarket Square. The façade on St. George’s Mall combines Art Deco and classical features
in plaster and concrete, which are painted white. Geologically, the familiar Paarl Grey granite
is the only rock present and occurs as polished cladded slabs on the ground floor and builds plinth
blocks below the columns of a concrete colonnade and balcony on St. George’s Mall. The light grey,
medium-grained, slightly porphyritic granite has a similar texture and mineralogy to that just seen in
several buildings along St. George’s Mall.</string>

    <!-- loc_26 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_26">Nedbank </string>
    <string name="loc_26_coords">-33.923419, 18.420758 \n\n 85 St. George\'s Mall </string>
    <string name="loc_26_desc">This building was completed in 1907 and was designed by architects W. Black, H. Black and G. Fagg,
who were placed first and second in submissions for a competition staged for the project by the New
York Mutual Insurance Company. The seven storey, steel framed building is highly decorated
with swag, egg and dart mouldings and fluted pilasters. Very light grey, coarse-grained,
porphyritic granite of the Cape Granite Suite, which was presumably taken from the Higgo Quarry
near Kloof Nek, builds the ground floor basework in a rustic finish and clads the first floor and
entrances in a sawn finish. The inaccessible upper floors are reportedly faced in “cream terracotta”,
including the carved ornamentation, but from street level, this has the appearance of a white
sandstone. The granite, which can be inspected at street level, is similar to that previously seen at
the Mandela-Rhodes Building, with the elongate laths (phenocrysts) of orthoclase being the most
prominent feature. Interestingly, a former entrance to the bank has been clad with Paarl Grey
granite, perhaps because the local quarries supplying coarse-grained, porphyritic granite had been
closed by the time this entrance was being blocked up. This is a useful spot to compare and contrast
the texture and mineralogy of the two local Cape granites.</string>

    <!-- loc_27 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_27">First National Bank</string>
    <string name="loc_27_coords">-33.923234, 18.421036 \n\n 81 St. George\'s Mall </string>
    <string name="loc_27_desc">This building was completed in 1907 under the supervision of architects Milne and Sladdin and is
26 years older than the building in Adderley Street with only the Paarl Grey medium-grained granite
being present in both buildings. The St. George’s Mall building comprises a five storey, steel or
concrete framed building with a prominent corner portico and three raised, inset, columned porticos
in St. George’s Mall, on the corner of the building and in Shortmarket Street, respectively. A
beige sandstone ashlar contrasts with red faggot brickwork on the facade. The corner portico, raised
inset porticos, cornices and window surrounds are built of sandstone, whereas the basework on the
ground floor, steps, a window surround in St. George’s Mall and cladded slabs at the entrance to the
bank consist of Paarl Grey granite.
    \n\n
        The sandstone is very fine- to fine-grained, massive and contains subrounded to subangular quartz
grains, silvery, flaky crystals of sericite and rare black, mafic minerals within a white clayey matrix.
Some of the slabs show weathering and flaking, particularly at the contact with the granite basework.
Cement mortar repair of some slabs has been carried out. The sandstone is most likely a Permian
Karoo sandstone and was probably exploited from quarries in the vicinity of Sasolburg or
Vereeniging, which were connected by railway to Cape Town during the time that the building was
constructed, i.e. after 1892. The granite is similar to that previously seen, i.e. light grey, mediumgrained,
slightly porphyritic with phenocrysts of white to light grey feldspar, up to 30 mm long, and
noticeable black flaky crystals of biotite within the groundmass.
        \n\n
        The building opposite First National Bank in St. George’s Mall, Market House, is rich in geology and is
location 28. Before reaching Market House, the participants should be aware of a street
sculpture in the central intersection of St. George’s Mall and Shortmarket Street. It takes the form of
a compass and clock, was sculptured by Fritha Langerman and Katherine Bull, is named “Come to
Pass” and was unveiled on 30th January 2006. It is composed of two sets of six units (glass and
bronze discs that echo each other formally), which intersect to form a cross and correspond to a
further 24 glass units (cats eyes) encircling the cross. The cast bronze discs identify six distinct
occupations that have been instrumental in the colonial evolution of the Cape cityscape (explorer,
settler, merchant, preacher, soldier, architect) and make up one axis of the cross. The other axis of
the cross, composed of six stainless steel rings framing the glass composite portraits, is constructed
from the information gathered from women that were previously interviewed. Each stainless steel
ring is engraved with a fictitious name and date composed from four of the twenty four women
interviewed. The 24 women’s names and occupations are recorded separately on the 24 cats eyes
encircling the cross.
    </string>

    <!-- loc_28 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_28">Market House</string>
    <string name="loc_28_coords">-33.922972, 18.420772 \n\n Corner of St George's Mall and Shortmarket St</string>
    <string name="loc_28_desc">Market House, which is a nine storey, steel or concrete framed building that was designed by W.H.
Grant and completed around 1932, has one of the most prominent Art Deco facades in Cape Town. Three South African igneous rocks are present on the ground and first floors, but creamcoloured,
precast facings dominate the building from the second floor upwards. Here,
there is a frieze of stylized proteas and disas (Cape Town City Council, 1987) and bas-relief eagles are
positioned above the entrances.
    \n\n
    The rocks occur as cladding, with the most abundant being a pink, hammer-dressed granite on the
upper part of the ground floor and the first floor. A black, fine-grained, polished gabbro,
which is strictly a fine-grained dolerite or basalt, is present on the lower part of the ground floor and
an orange and red migmatitic to gneissic, polished granite with grey to dark grey and black
convoluted bands, patches, stringers and streaks, occurs at the extreme southwestern end of the
ground floor. The pink granite is medium- to coarse-grained with pink feldspar crystals,
probably orthoclase, and very light grey to white, lath-like, feldspar crystals, which are beigecoloured
in places and show a red tinge. Black flaky crystals of biotite are present, as well as less
conspicuous grey, glassy quartz crystals. The granite is from the former Transvaal, South Africa,
and resembles one of the granites of the Precambrian Bushveld Complex from the area north of
Pretoria. It is approximately 2050 million years old. The black “gabbro” contains barely visible
grey to dark grey, lath-like crystals of plagioclase and black pyroxene crystals. It is similar to gabbros
from the Bushveld Complex and may have been derived from the Bon Accord area, north of Pretoria. The black colour of the rock is due to the presence of minute needles of magnetite in the
plagioclase crystals. It has a similar age to the pink granite. The migmatitic to gneissic granite
is the Parys Granite, which was seen at the South African Mutual Life Assurance Society Building
(location 8). It may have been exploited from the Municipal Quarry at Parys, Free State, given the 1930s
age of the building. The granite is fine- to very coarse-grained and contains pink to red feldspar
crystals, which show microfractures with a red ferruginous infill, very light grey to grey, glassy quartz
crystals, and black flaky crystals of biotite, which are more abundant in the darker convoluted bands,
patches, stringers and streaks. The cross-cutting pseudotachylite veins, which are fairly common in
this granite, were not observed.</string>

    <!-- loc_29 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_29">Number 86 St. George\'s Mall</string>
    <string name="loc_29_coords">-33.922796, 18.420896 \n\n Number 86 St. George\'s Mall</string>
    <string name="loc_29_desc">This is a seven storey, steel or concrete framed building, which shows a Cape Revival Italianate style. Attached giant order columns and baluster balconettes occur on the fifth and sixth floors and it
was completed in 1925, but the name of the architect is not known. Natural stones are confined
to the ground floor, with the remainder of the building being plastered and painted beige. Locallyquarried,
fine- to coarse-grained, quartzitic sandstone of the Table Mountain Group, in a rustic finish,
forms the basework on the ground floor and is present in archways above the ground floor. Polished
cladding of Parys Granite similar to that just seen at Market House, occurs at pavement level and
around the basal part of the entrance, including the steps. A black, fine-grained gabbro also similar in
appearance to the gabbro at Market House, makes up the nose of the treads of three steps at the
entrance to the building. It was most likely derived from the 2050 million year-old Bushveld Complex
north of Pretoria.</string>

    <!-- loc_30 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_30">Waldorf Arcade</string>
    <string name="loc_30_coords">-33.922344, 18.420882 \n\n Shortmarket St </string>
    <string name="loc_30_desc">The Waldorf Arcade was
completed in 1988, replacing
both the old Waldorf and
Morkels buildings. The
architects were Mallows, Louw,
Hoffe and Orme, who received a
project award in 1984 from the
magazine Architecture SA, in
recognition of their ability to
blend in this building with the
surrounding buildings and street
facades. The Waldorf
Arcade is an eleven storey,
concrete framed building that
extends between St. George’s
Mall and Burg Street and has a
ground level arched entrance
and collonaded front on St.
George’s Mall. Polished red
granite clads the columns of the
collonade, first floor balconies,
ground, first and second floor
facade and the arched entrance,
and polished dark grey to black
gabbro clads the columns and
ground floor at pavement level.
    \n\n
    The red granite is coarse-grained, slightly porphyritic with reddish-pink feldspar (orthoclase?)
phenocrysts. This feldspar is also present in the groundmass and is microfractured with a red
ferruginous infill. Some feldspars display a red tinge. Light grey to dark grey glassy quartz and
abundant black mafic minerals, including flaky biotite, can be discerned. The granite is referred to as
“Balmoral Red” in the Stone Trade and was quarried from Finland. This name dates from the late-19th century, when Scandinavian granites were first
being quarried for building stone and were initially shipped in block to be cut and polished in the
stoneyards of Aberdeen. Under these conditions, names associated in any way with Royal
Deeside were more prestigious than local Scandinavian names. The granite is situated in the root
zone of the Caledonian (450 to 350 million years ago) fold belt of southern Finland, where
deformation continued after the original intrusion of the granite. This accounts for the
microfracturing in the feldspar, which is associated with tectonic deformation. The gabbro is from
the 2050 million year-old Bushveld Complex and is termed “Rustenburg Grey”, being sourced from
the area between Brits and Rustenburg. We have already seen examples of this stone at the City
Hall (location 7). The gabbro is coarse-grained and contains grey to light grey, plagioclase crystals, some
of which show a dark brown alteration product. By definition, there is an absence of quartz, and the
black-coloured crystals in the groundmass consist of pyroxene. The remainder of the building
above the second floor is clad with precast concrete panels with an exposed pebble finish.</string>

    <!-- loc_31 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_31">South African Reserve Bank</string>
    <string name="loc_31_coords">-33.921958, 18.421177 \n\n 25 Burg St and Hout st </string>
    <string name="loc_31_desc">The high-rise office tower of the Reserve Bank, which dominates the skyline, was designed by
architect H. van der Merwe and completed in 1976. It shows extensive aluminium and glass
curtain walling with the corner facings clad in very light grey to white-coloured material. This
material, which is obviously inaccessible, is apparently composed of granite from Spitzkoppe, some
60 km west of Usakos in Namibia, is about 130 million years old and is known in the Stone Trade as
“Namibian Pearl”. It was only assembled in 1991,
when the original ceramic tile cladding was replaced.
    \n\n
        Two accessible natural stones are present around the podium of the office tower. Polished Paarl
Grey granite clads the first, second and third floors of the podium, as well as the canopy face above
the main entrance, whereas a markedly contrasting black, fine-grained, polished dolerite clads the
ground floor and the walls near the main entrance. The Paarl Grey granite is similar to that seen on
the previous buildings visited, i.e. it is light grey, medium-grained and slightly porphyritic with white
and very light grey, lath-like, feldspar phenocrysts, up to 20 mm long. The dolerite is named
“Zimbabwe Black” in the Stone Trade and comes from the Mutoko area of Zimbabwe, about 140 km
northeast of Harare. Stratigraphically, it belongs to the Mashonaland Dolerite Suite and is
approximately 1835 million years old. Grey to dark grey rectangular-shaped plagioclase crystals,
some showing a brown iridescent alteration product and a few displaying twinning, can be vaguely
seen in the dolerite, which otherwise contains black pyroxene and rare, black, fine-grained cubic
magnetite crystals.
    </string>

    <!-- loc_32 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_32">Allianz House (54 St. George’s Mall)</string>
    <string name="loc_32_coords">-33.922021, 18.421706 \n\n 54 St. George’s Mall </string>
    <string name="loc_32_desc">This building was originally named Atlas House when it was constructed in 1938, which later became
Boston House College and finally Allianz House when the college moved in 2015. The nine
storey, steel or concrete framed building was designed by the architectural firm of Hawke and
McKinlay. It has a bronze, crouching Atlas sculpture outside the third floor and an ornate,
travertine urn in a recessed corner of the sixth floor. The creamy white travertine is the predominant
rock type and clads the building from the third floor upwards. It is inaccessible and its origin is
unknown. However, two accessible granites, which we have seen earlier, are present on the ground
floor. The most extensive is a pink, hammer-dressed granite that clads the ground, first and second
floors and forms the balconies and corner pedestal on the third floor. This granite, which clads part
of Market House (location 28), a short distance back along the mall, is from the Precambrian
Bushveld Complex in the region north of Pretoria. It is medium- to coarse-grained with pink, very
light grey and white, lath-like, feldspar crystals that show a red tinge. Black flaky crystals of biotite
are present, as well as less conspicuous grey, irregular-shaped, glassy quartz crystals. The second
granite is the ubiquitous Paarl Grey, which forms the basework of the ground floor in a rustic and
sawn finish.</string>

    <!-- loc_33 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_33">Woolworths Building</string>
    <string name="loc_33_coords">
-33.922027, 18.422527 \n\n 31 St Georges Mall </string>
    <string name="loc_33_desc">Two rock types are present in the form of polished cladding on the ground floor. The Woolworths
Building occupies the block bordered by St. George’s Mall, Strand Street, Adderley Street and Castle
Street. It was completed in 1975 using the architects Fridjohn, Fulford and Callinicias and is a
four storey, concrete framed building constructed by Murray and Roberts (Pty) Ltd.
    \n\n
    The more abundant rock type is
pale pink granite, which
clads the ground floor supporting
walls between extensive window
panes. This granite originates from
the Vigo region in Galicia, western
Spain and is known as “Rosa
Porrino” in the Stone Trade. It is coarsegrained,
slightly porphyritic with
pink lath-like orthoclase
phenocrysts containing biotite
inclusions and microfractures with
a pinkish-red ferruginous infill. The
groundmass contains grey to light
grey, glassy quartz, white to very
light grey feldspar and black, flaky
crystals of biotite. Some of the
white to very light grey feldspar
crystals show colour zoning
between light green, light yellowish
green and grey, and also a red
tinge in places. Rare black speckled
xenoliths and mafic minerals are
present. This granite is Permian in
age.
    \n\n
    A black, fine-grained, polished gabbro, which is strictly a fine-grained dolerite or basalt, clads the
ground floor supporting walls beneath the granite at pavement level. It is known as
“Rustenburg Grey” in the Stone Trade and resembles the
fine-grained variety seen at Market House (location 30) rather than the normal coarse-grained variety
seen at City Hall and Waldorf Arcade (locations 7 and 30). It is difficult to distinguish the grey
plagioclase crystals within the black-coloured, pyroxene-rich groundmass of the gabbro. The gabbro
is from the 2050 million year-old Bushveld Complex and may have been derived from the Bon Accord
area, north of Pretoria. Precast concrete panels with an exposed aggregate finish are present
above the ground floor.</string>

    <!-- loc_34 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_34">Fountain In St. George\'s Mall</string>
    <string name="loc_34_coords">-33.922004, 18.422027 </string>
    <string name="loc_34_desc">Three varieties of granite from the Cape Granite Suite are present. The familiar light grey to very light
grey, coarse-grained, porphyritic granite, which shows its usual characteristics, i.e. white to very light
grey orthoclase phenocrysts (some twinned), up to 100 mm long, grey glassy quartz, light grey to
white, rectangular-shaped feldspar, black, flaky crystals of biotite and sparse, dark grey to black
xenoliths, some of which are partly assimilated by the granite, builds most of the fountain structure,
including a canal that links an upper and lower fountain. A less abundant light grey, medium- to
coarse-grained granite is present in the fountain structure and has a similar mineralogy, but the
orthoclase phenocrysts are less than 20 mm in length. Another type of granite, namely a quartz
porphyry, which we see for the first and only time, is present as smaller stone blocks on the outer
sides of the canal walls and in some steps. The porphyry is dark grey and has a fine-grained
groundmass that contains phenocrysts of grey, glassy quartz, black, flaky biotite and brown, greyish
brown and light grey feldspar. It resembles the Saldanha Quartz Porphyry, which is a late-phase
igneous event of the Cape Granite Suite. This porphyry was quarried for dimension stone and
stone aggregate in the vicinity of Saldanha, where it represents a shallow, magmatic intrusive
phase coeval with a succession of volcanic ignimbrite flows situated some 6 km south of Saldanha on
the Postberg Peninsula. These ignimbrite flows yielded a U-Pb zircon age of 515.5 ± 3.1 Ma.
    \n\n
    The fountain was probably built around 1992 after the conversion of St George’s Street to a mall. At
this time, all the local granite quarries had been closed, and the granites were obtained from
recycled stone belonging to Cape Town City Council.</string>

    <!-- loc_35 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_35">Norton Rose House</string>
    <string name="loc_35_coords">-33.919858, 18.423473 \n\n Southeastern corner of Thibault Square in front
of Riebeek Street
 </string>
    <string name="loc_35_desc">
    Norton Rose House was completed in 1986 with Louis Karol being the architect. It is a three storey,
concrete or steel framed building that occupies the southeastern corner of Thibault Square in front
of Riebeek Street. Geologically, two granites are present cladding the exterior columns of the
ground floor in St. George’s Mall and cladding the columns that support a canopy in Thibault Square..
        \n\n
A red coarse-grained granite clads the top
and base of the columns, whilst a pale
pink granite clads the centre of the
columns. The red granite is
referred to as “Balmoral Red” in the Stone
Trade and we have already inspected this
granite outside the Waldorf Arcade (location
30). It was quarried from the root zone of
the Caledonian (450 to 350 million years
ago) fold belt of southern Finland, where
deformation continued after the original
intrusion of the granite. We have also
seen the pale pink granite at the
Woolworths Building (location 33), which is
referred to as “Rosa Porrino” in the Stone
Trade. This granite originates
from the Vigo region in Galicia, western
Spain and is Permian in age. The
remainder of the building contains
precast concrete slabs.
    </string>

    <!-- loc_36 -->
    <string name="title_activity_loc_36">Pier Place</string>
    <string name="loc_36_coords"> -33.917820, 18.425751 </string>
    <string name="loc_36_desc">Pier Place is a fourteen storey,
concrete or steel framed structure
that was designed by Louis Karol
Architects and completed in 1991.
It is clad with precast concrete
panels containing an exposed
aggregate finish.
However, the columns and pillars
at ground floor level are clad with
polished, pinkish-red granite and
layers of polished, dark grey to
black gabbro. The pinkish-red
granite is medium- to coarsegrained
and porphyritic with
phenocrysts of lath-like, pinkish-red
microcline. The
groundmass minerals are less
conspicuous and consist of pink,
light grey and very light grey
feldspar, which shows a red tinge
in places, grey to light grey, glassy
quartz and sparse black, flaky
biotite. The granite is from the
Salem Granite Suite in the vicinity
of Karibib in Namibia and is
known as “Karibib Red” in the
Stone Trade, being similar in age to
the Cape Granite Suite (~ 550
million years old). The gabbro is a
variant of Rustenburg Grey and is
similar to that seen at the Waldorf
Arcade (location 30). It is coarsegrained
and some of the grey to
light grey, rectangular-shaped
crystals of plagioclase are twinned
or show a dark brown alteration
product. The black minerals are
mostly pyroxene.</string>


    <!-- ROCK VALUES -->
    <string name="rock_locs_label">Locations that this stone is found at:</string>

    <!-- 1, 2, 3, 4, 9, 10, 13, 15, 16 19, 21, 22, 23,24,25, 26, 27, 31, 32 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_1">Paarl Grey granite</string>

    <!-- (2, 3, 10, 14, 17, 29)-->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_2">Quartzitic Sandstone</string>

    <!-- 5, 17, 20 [malmesbury] & other -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_3">Slate</string>

    <!-- 1, 3, 6, 7, 11, 15, 19, 20, 26, 34,  -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_4">Porphyritic granite of the Cape Granite Suite</string>

    <!-- 7, 30, 33, 36 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_5">Rustenburg Grey black gabbro</string>

    <!-- 8, 28, 29 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_6">Parys granite</string>

    <!-- Mentioned at 27, 19 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_7">Permian Karoo sandstone</string>

    <!-- Mentioned at 1 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_8">Golden Dawn sandstone</string>

    <!-- Mentioned at 36 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_9">Karibib Red granite</string>

    <!-- 30, 35 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_10">Balmoral Red</string>

    <!-- 23, 4 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_11">Syenite</string>

    <!--  5,  [europe] -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_12">Leucogabbro</string>

    <!--  12 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_13">Marble</string>

    <!--  31 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_14">Namibian Pearl granite</string>

    <!--  7,20 [england] -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_15">Limestone</string>

    <!--  33, 35 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_16">Rosa Porrino granite</string>

    <!--  20 [scotland] -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_17">Peterhead granite</string>

    <!--  7 [england] -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_18">Bath Stone</string>

    <!--  20 [britain] -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_20">New Red Sandstone</string>

    <!--  20 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_21">Ficksburg Sandstone</string>

    <!--  10, 32 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_22">Travertine</string>

    <!--  28, 32 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_23">Pink hammer-dressed granite</string>

    <!--  31 -->
    <string name="title_activity_rock_24">Zimbabwe black dolerite</string>

    <string name="title_activity_about">About</string>

    <string name="refs_1">[1] Cole D (2002) Popular Science Series 3, Council for Geoscience, South Africa, 132p \n\n</string>
<string name="refs_2">[2] Armstrong R et al. (1998) Special Abstracts, J Afr Earth Sci 27\: 10-12 \n\n
[3] Frimmel H et al. (2013) Precambrian Res 231\: 218-235 \n\n
[4] Rozendaal A et al. (1999) Precambrian Res 97\: 303-323 \n\n </string>
    <!--[5] Scheepers R and Cuney M (1992) Ore Geol Rev 7\: 1-23 \n\n
    [6] Chemale F et al. (2011) Int J Earth Sci 100\: 431-444\n\n
    [7] Theron J (1984) Geology Cape Town and environs\: Sheet Explanation\: Geol Surv, South Africa, 77p\n\n
    [8] Cocks L and Fortey R (1986) Geol Mag 123\: 437-444\n\n
    [9] Broquet C (1990) Abstract, Geocongress ’90, Geol Soc South Africa, 64-67\n\n
    [10] Compton J (2006) The Rocks and Mountains of Cape Town\: Double Storey, Cape Town, 112p \n\n
    [11] https://site.google.com/site/gssawcb Table Mountain\: Natural Wonder of the World\n\n
    [12] Newton R et al. (2006) In: The Geology of South Africa\: Geol Soc South Africa, 521-530\n\n
    [13] Wickins P (1986) Africa 1880-1980: An Economic History\: Oxford Univ Press, Cape Town, 321p\n\n
    [14] Hilton (2010) The Cape Town Foreshore Plan\: https://www.flickr.com/photos/hilton-t/4497701380\n\n
    [15] Crump A and Van Niekerk, R (1988) Public Sculptures and Reliefs, Cape Town: Clifton Publications, Cape
    Town, 71p\n\n
    [16] Oosterhuis W (1999) Stone in Southern Africa\: Unesco Publishing, Paris, 56p</string>\n\n
        [17] Felix J (2013) Tough Task to Move War Statue\: Cape Times, 22 July 2013.\n\n
        [18] Wybergh W (1932) Memoir 29, Geol Surv, South Africa, 244p\n\n
        [19] Broquet C (1992) In\: Inversion Tectonics of the Cape Fold Belt, Karoo and Cretaceous Basins of Southern
        Africa: Balkema, Rotterdam, 159-183\n\n
        [20] Watson J (1911) British and Foreign Building Stones\: Cambridge Univ Press, Cambridge, 483p\n\n
        [21] De Villiers S (1985) A Tale of Three Cities\: Creda Press, Cape Town, 112p\n\n
        [22] Hartdegen P (1988) Our Building Heritage\: An Illustrated History: Printpak Books, Cape Town, 312p\n\n
        [23] Scheepers R and Schoch A (2006) In\: The Geology of South Africa: Geol Soc South Africa, 421-432\n\n
        [24] Department of Planning (1971) The Natural Dimension Stone Industry\: Report, Department of Planning,
        South Africa, 131p.\n\n
        [25] Verwoerd W (2006) In: The Geology of South Africa: Geol Soc South Africa, 381-393\n\n
        [26] Lazareth C and Mercier J (1999) In\: Geoarchaeology\: Exploration, Environments, Resources: Geol Soc
        London 165: 123-137\n\n
        [27] Hall M et al. (1993) South Afr J Sci 89\: 110-112\n\n
        [28] Fransen H and Cook M (1980) The Old Buildings of the Cape\: Balkema, Cape Town, 456p \n\n
        [29] Rennie J (1978) The Buildings of Central Cape Town\: Vol 2 – Catalogue\: Cape Provincial Institute of
        Architects\: Mills Litho (Pty) Ltd, Cape Town, 369p\n\n
        [30] Picton-Seymour D (1977) Victorian Buildings in South Africa, 1850-1910\: Balkema, Rotterdam, 412p\n\n
        [31] Rennie J and Riley P (1987) Cape Town City Hall\: Report, City Planners’ Department, City of Cape Town,
        South Africa, 115p\n\n
        [32] Robinson E (1985) London – Illustrated Geological Walks (Book 2)\: The Universities Press (Belfast) Ltd,
        142p\n\n
        [33] Gibson et al. (2000) S Afr J Geol 103\: 175-190\n\n
        [34] Reimold W and Koeberl C (1994) Geobulletin 37 (3)\: 3-7\n\n
        [35] Kamo et al. (1996) Earth Planet Sci Lett 144\: 369-388\n\n
        [36] Cape Town City Council (1987) Cape town Historical Walks – Central City\: Galvin and Sales, Cape Town, 31p\n\n
        [37] Gresse P and Theron J (1992) Geology Worcester area\: Sheet Explanation\: Geol Surv, South Africa, 79p\n\n
        [38] Greig D (1970) Herbert Baker in South Africa\: Purnell, Cape Town, 276p\n\n
        [39] Oosterhuis W (1998) Handbook 16, Council for Geoscience, South Africa, 259-266\n\n
        [40] Keath M (1990) Herbert Baker, Architecture and Idealism 1892-1913, the South African Years\: Ashanti
        Publishing Limited, Gibraltar, 246p\n\n
        [41] Robinson E (1984) London – Illustrated Geological Walks (Book 1)\: The Universities Press (Belfast) Ltd, 98p\n\n
        [42] Woods H (1961) Palaeontology Invertebrate\: Cambridge Univ Press, Cambridge, 477p\n\n
        [43] Public Sculpture Projects (2015) Come to Pass\: http\://ava.co.za/public-sculpture-projects/\n\n
        [44] Cole D (2003) Metallogeny Cape Town area\: Sheet Explanation\: Council for Geoscience, South Africa, 80p\n\n
        [45] Scheepers R and Poujol M (2002) S Afr J Geol 105\: 163-178\n\n
        [46] Brett Murray (2015) Africa\: https\://www.reddit.com/r/TheSimpsons/comments/3be3ko/bart_simpson_
        sculpture_in_cape_town_south_africa/?\n\n
        [47] Pier Place (2012) \: http\://able.wiki.up.ac.za/index.php/Pier_Place_(Heerengracht_street_Cape_Town)\n\n -->

</resources>
